Good morning. Today's דף daf is פ"ג Pey Gimmel where we're going
to wrap up the sixth פרק, perek, השוכר את האומנין, Haskocher es
ha'Umnim, and go to השוכר את הפועלים. Hasocher es ha'Poalim. But just
to sort of summarize briefly some of the points from the last
משנה, mishna, which is an important משנה, mishna, the משנה mishna dealt
with the issue about workers that were carrying a barrel from a
wine or whatever it was that they were watching. Actually, the case
wasn't workers; the case was watchers or שומר, shomer, שומר שכר shomer
sachar or שומר חינם, shomer chinam, and they tripped presumably, it slipped
and it broke. So are they liable or not? So the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says they take an oath if they weren't negligent,
which or by way as they take an oath and they're exempt.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, yes, I know they take an
oath, or רב אלעזר Rav Elazar really I think is the correct
גרסא, gersa, but I don't understand why they take an oath because
logically they should be liable. And the גמרא Gemara has a middle
position, says the first one is the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, and has a middle position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
says perhaps the most logical thing, which is that a שומר חינם
shomer chinam swears and is exempt and a שומר שכר shomer sachar
pays. So a שומר חינם shomer chinam pays only in cases of
negligence. A שומר שכר shomer sachar pays in cases of גניבה ואבידה,
gneiva v'aveida, if it's stolen or it's lost, but conceptually that really
is a case of not doesn't need to be full negligence. On
the other hand, it's not an אונס. ones. It's not something that
was completely, you know, you were completely blameless about and completely out
of your control. So what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying is
a very logical position. When a barrel slips and breaks, we don't
necessarily consider you to be negligent.
Certainly if you swear you weren't negligent, you know, then there could
be other reasons, but on the other hand, it wasn't totally out
of your control. You know what they say? Accidents don't just happen.
Right? You know, there's things you could have done and whatever. So
he says it's a middle level of it's not full negligence but
it's not full faultlessness and therefore רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a
שומר שכר shomer sachar pays and a שומר חינם shomer chinam is
exempt. Makes a lot of sense. What is the position of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir was the challenge of the גמרא. Gemara. Now you
could say and what the גמרא Gemara says in one possibility is
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir they were it was it was
like
an אונס, ones, even a שומר שכר shomer sachar is exempt. We
consider that if you trip and you break, it's completely you're completely
blameless.
Maybe that's a possible position, but the problem is is that we
have another position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that if
you are carrying something and you trip and it breaks and then
the shards caused somebody, you know, to be damaged. It's a בבא
קמא Bava Kamma question: did you make the בור? bor? Were you
negligent as a result of it tripping and breaking and therefore when
somebody is injured as a result that was due to your negligence,
right, and you're like you've made a בור bor is the concept
there, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that actually you have made
a בור, bor, you were negligent. So what do you do with
that contradiction? How can you go from one place to say you
have like full negligence to another position to say like you're totally
blameless? One minute, one minute. And the גמרא's Gemara answer is, the
first answer of the גמרא Gemara is you're right, they're completely different
positions on what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. According to one תנא,
tanna, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're completely blameless when something trips
that you're carrying and it breaks, and according to the other תנא
tanna you're completely negligent, like one extreme to the other. So that
was sort of like the first answer of the גמרא, Gemara, that
there's two completely different versions of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says no, it falls into the middle category. שומר שכר
shomer sachar is חייב, chayav, שומר חינם shomer chinam is exempt. And
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says I know the tradition is like רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but I don't understand it. First of all, I
think certainly the שומר שכר shomer sachar should be חייב. chayav. Probably
even a שומר חינם shomer chinam should be חייב chayav if it's
negligence especially if it was like at a, you know, if it
was at an angle.
I mean if it wasn't at an angle, if you were going
down an incline I understand you weren't negligent, but on flat ground
even a שומר חינם shomer chinam should be negligent. And anyway, even
if they weren't negligent they should have or it's possible lack of
negligence would get them off, they should need to bring witnesses. I
don't believe necessarily their oath quoting the position of איסי בן יהודה
Issi ben Yehuda that says that if there's possibly witnesses around, you
don't get exempt by an oath. So I don't understand any of
this. But that's the tradition I'm reviewing.
But that's the קבלת רבותי, kabbalat rabotai, but that's the position that
I have a tradition of. So what's the explanation of that position
if it doesn't make any sense? So the גמרא Gemara concludes last
line or whatever from yesterday's דף, daf, top line of פ"ג עמוד
א', daf Pey Gimmel amud Aleph, the גמרא Gemara says
רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, I'm sorry no. So
it doesn't actually, I take it back, it doesn't have an answer.
We're going to see an answer in a minute, but he says
I know that's the tradition but I don't understand why it makes
sense. Okay, so basically that is approach number one. There's a debate
whether רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's full negligence or total blamelessness,
but within the position it's blamelessness you're fully exempt. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says it's in the middle category. שומר שכר shomer sachar is
liable, שומר חינם shomer chinam is exempt. And רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
says I know the tradition is like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar excuse me, was like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but
it doesn't make sense. You should obviously there's many reasons you should
be liable. Rabbi Dov, you had a question.
So apparently you can compare negligence on the breaking of an object
to negligence associated with personal injury in נזק? nezek? Yeah, I mean
the question is are you negligent?
I mean that was a case in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. So,
apparently you can compare negligence on the breaking of an object to
negligence associated with personal injury in נזק? Nezek? Yeah, I mean, the
question is are you neg-, I mean, that's what was a case
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma itself, right? It had a case where
you tripped and you were negligent or whatever, there's one question about
do you pay, like there's, you know, do you pay if somebody
else gets injured as a result, do you pay for breaking the
thing or whatever. Right. The first question, was the fact of the
tripping and it breaking negligence? And then it has multiple implications. Okay.
Alright, תוספות Tosafot makes the point that you're only liable for making
a בור bor if there's full negligence, which is why it's so
strange that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir takes like opposite positions. In one
place he seems to say full negligence, in another he seems to
say complete blamelessness, which is why the גמרא Gemara says its first
answer the גמרא Gemara said it's two positions within רבי מאיר. Rebbe
Meir. We'll see another answer in a minute. Yes.
They were comparing different things, one was I accidentally tripped and broke
your thing, the other was I tripped and broke something and left
it there.
Well, no, because the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara over
there says, right, you could say the blame is for leaving it
there, but the גמרא Gemara says the case there was you were
מפקיר mafkir it after you fell. So therefore if you were מפקיר
mafkir at the moment after you fell and you were blameless when
it fell, then and then you said I give, I'm like I
give up possession of it, then you're not seen as being responsible
for leaving it there. You're only seen as being responsible for leaving
it there if either you were responsible for breaking it or you
owned it after it was there and the owning it after it
was there made you responsible for cleaning it up. But if you
were smart enough to be מפקיר mafkir at the minute after it
broke, okay, well that's but that's the position of the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara though says that in that scenario the only
liability we can hold, the only way we can get you is
for the initial act of tripping and that's how come it's comparable.
Okay, now I do want to point out a very important there's
a big תוספות Tosafot here which it this this what which he
as the big תוספות Tosafot which he asks a question that is
not in the גמרא Gemara but is very important, it's really a
בבא קמא Bava Kamma question so I'll just mention briefly here. And
תוספות Tosafot says the following, תוספות Tosafot says I don't get any
of this, says תוספות. Tosafot. Let's say okay, according to the position,
here's the easiest way to appreciate תוספות's Tosafot question. According to the
position that you have a middle level of negligence, right, that a
שומר שכר shomer sachar would pay and a שומר חינם shomer chinam
wouldn't. He says, why would a שומר חינם shomer chinam not pay
when you trip and break somebody else's barrel? Maybe you're not liable
as a שומר, shomer, but why aren't you liable as a מזיק?
mazik? You broke his barrel and we say, you know, you with
your own hand broke the barrel and don't tell me you were
blameless or you weren't a high negligence, we say אדם מועד לעולם
adam muad le'olam that a person is always liable for acts of
מזיק mazik even if he was blameless. So why are you liable
for breaking somebody's barrel, why are you exempt for breaking somebody's barrel
if you're a שומר חינם? shomer chinam? That's תוספות's Tosafot question. And
this leads and he deals with other גמרות Gemaras as well. This
leads תוספות Tosafot to the conclusion that a, that a אדם המזיק,
adam hamazik, even though the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא Bava Kamma
said is מועד לעולם, muad le'olam, is always liable regardless of fault,
it didn't really mean it. It really is you need a certain
degree of fault. So you have the you need to be as
and actually according to תוספות Tosafot you need a like a pretty
high degree of fault. You need the fault that's comparable to what
he would call like גניבה, geneivah, like I'm sorry, the fault comparable
to אבידה, aveidah, the type of fault that would lead to an
object getting lost, which is a pretty a pretty high degree of
fault. Only in that case are you are you liable as an
אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. But like you know if you sort of
think about it as a continuum,
right, here's gross
negligence and that's a שומר חינם shomer chinam pays and then the
next level and that's on a continuum of degree of fault, right,
this is אונס, ones, right,
and then within what a שומר שכר shomer sachar pays there's two
levels, right, there's
there's אבידה aveidah that's obviously you're more to blame when it got
lost than when it got stolen. Alright, so that's like your continuum.
So what תוספות Tosafot says is when an אדם, adam, when we
say אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad le'olam, that would suggest you're חייב
chayav in all those cases, right, always, right, even blameless. תוספות Tosafot
says no, no, אדם מועד לעולם adam muad le'olam really just means
you're חייב chayav in these cases. So he completely redefines what the
גמרא Gemara means. Okay, and that's why if you're שומר שכר shomer
sachar you take an, if we say that this idea of tripping
or whatever, right, is in this category, if tripping is in this
category, so if you're שומר חינם shomer chinam you weren't negligent. If
you're שומר שכר shomer sachar you pay because it's up here, but
you're not going to pay as an אדם המזיק adam hamazik because
it is higher than this sort of level of negligence. Yes, Jenna.
I just want to answer, you're
supposedly the agent and therefore like why I don't understand why אדם
מועד לעולם adam muad le'olam would apply to a place where you're...
Ah, so what Jenna says is excellent. What Jenna's saying is basically
the answer that רמב"ן Ramban gives, or he implies. And רמב"ן Ramban
rejects all of תוספות's Tosafot proofs that אדם adam is not מועד
לעולם. muad le'olam. And he says yes, the אדם adam is מועד
לעולם, muad le'olam, of course, you're always paying. But that and it's
not like you need a certain degree of negligence. But says רמב"ן,
Ramban, there are some exceptions. Not because you weren't negligent enough, but
because there's something else to be considering. For example, a whole series
of cases that תוספות Tosafot shows that you're exempt. He says it's
not because you were less negligent, it's because the person who got
damaged was to blame himself. So if I go ahead and you're
lying down and you're sleeping and I lie next to you and
you hit me in the middle of the night, it's not because
you the you're exempt. Not because you weren't at blame, it's because
I was to blame lying down next to
you in range where you could bump into me in the middle
of the night. I brought it on myself. So that's a different
category. That's not your lack of negligence, that's due to my
fault and in this case the רמב"ן Ramban doesn't say this, this
is what the אחרונים Achronim explain for the רמב"ן, Ramban, it's like
you don't get to call the guy an אדם המזיק. Adam Hamazik.
An אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik is somebody who did not have rights
to be dealing with your object, whether they were willfully attacking, damaging
it, whether they fell on it and they tripped. But somebody who
was carrying around your barrel because you've hired them to watch your
object and they're doing what they're supposed to be doing and then
something happens and they slip, you cannot put say, oh well there
are two things, they're a שומר, Shomer, we have to say are
they liable as a שומר Shomer or was there negligence, and they're
also an אדם המזיק. Adam Hamazik. They're not an אדם המזיק. Adam
Hamazik. Their fundamental categorization is under laws of שומר. Shomer. That's the
place in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch where you look up how to
treat them. You don't get to sort of double categorize them. So
that's the other answer and that makes a lot of sense, but
it's important that תוספות Tosafos raises the question which is, so this
guy, it's not that he's fully negligent, the שומר חינם, Shomer Chinam,
but why isn't he paying as an אדם המזיק? Adam Hamazik? So
תוספות's Tosafos answer is you need even a certain degree of negligence
as an אדם המזיק. Adam Hamazik. The better answer is that you
don't get to categorize him as that, he's categorized as a שומר.
Shomer.
See the רמב"ן Ramban would invoke the principle in בבא קמא, Bava
Kamma, like you walk, you should have looked where you were going.
And if so, but the part saying it to the ניזק. Nizak.
Okay, so thank you very much again for this, thank you. Alright,
so now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says
like this: רב חייא, Reb Chiyah, five lines from the top. רב
חייא.
Reb
Chiyah. You got up to that?
Where you didn't
say, where's the very very top?
Oh, okay, I got it, okay, fine, fine, fine. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this:
ואפילו במקום מדרון, v'afilu b'makom midron, so repeat what we just said
before why רב אליעזר Reb Eliezer says this doesn't make sense. He
says, I don't get it. First of all, a שומר שכר Shomer
Sachar should be חייב. chayav. Second of all, even a שומר חינם
Shomer Chinam should be חייב chayav if it was a flat level,
then he would be negligent. ואפילו במקום מדרון, v'afilu b'makom midron, even
if he was going down an incline where you could say okay
that wasn't real negligence, he had to go down an incline and
it was slippery and whatever, נמי הכא היכא דליכא ראיה. nami hacha
heicha d'leika raya. That's fine if there's no way to bring any
evidence, then we would trust him with his שבועה. shevua. אבל היכא
דאיכא ראיה, aval heicha d'ika raya, if there were witnesses or some
evidence to bring, נייתי ראיה וליפטר, neisi raya u'leifter, he wouldn't be
allowed to just take an oath, he'd have to produce the proof.
דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraisa: איסי בן יהודה אומר
אין רואה, Isi ben Yehuda omer ein ro'eh, שבועת ה' תהיה בין
שניהם. shevuas Hashem tihiyeh bein shneihem. Something happened, there was nobody to
see it, the שומר Shomer gives an oath. שבועת ה' תהיה בין
שניהם. shevuas Hashem tihiyeh bein shneihem. הא יש רואה, Ha yesh ro'eh,
if there was somebody who witnessed it, יביא ראיה ויפטר, yavi raya
v'yepater, then you have to bring the proof. Okay, so he says,
so that's the range. One says you're completely blameless, one says you're
in the middle level, the other says I agree you should be
חייב chayav in many of these cases, but whatever reason we have
a tradition that you're פטור. patur. רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן, Reb Chiyah bar Abba amar Reb Yochanan, now רבי חייא בר
אבא Reb Chiyah bar Abba says in the name of רבי יוחנן
Reb Yochanan a different way to explain רבי מאיר's Reb Meir position:
that even though רבי מאיר Reb Meir normally says that a guy
who trips is negligent, here's why רבי מאיר Reb Meir says that
both fully negligent, so both should be חייב, chayav, which is essentially
רב אלעזר's Reb Elazar position, here, or here's why רבי מאיר Reb
Meir says that they're both exempt. Why? שבועה זו תקנת חכמים היא.
shevua zu takanas chachamim hi. Remember this רבי יוחנן, Reb Yochanan, you
might remember this goes back to the very beginning of בבא מציעא.
Bava Metzia. רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan consistently applies a lot of these
שבועות shevuos to not be like מעיקר הדין m'ikar hadin but a
special תקנה. takana. So there's one where people were grabbing onto a
טלית tallis and they both took an oath and he says it's
a תקנת חכמים takanas chachamim that you shouldn't go and grab somebody's
טלית tallis off somebody else's back and claim it's yours. So here
too. He says, now that means we imposed a שבועה. shevua. Here
actually allowing you to take a שבועה shevua and to be exempt.
Fundamentally following רבי מאיר, Reb Meir, everybody should be חייב, chayav, even
a שומר חינם, Shomer Chinam, you were negligent when you tripped. But
חז"ל Chazal are going to let you take a שבועה shevua and
be off. Why? שבועה זו תקנת חכמים היא, shevua zu takanas chachamim
hi, שאם אתה אומר כן, she-im atah omer ken,
if you don't let a שומר Shomer take a שבועה shevua and
be off and you say that you have to pay if you
trip and break something, אין לך אדם המעביר חבית לחברו ממקום למקום,
ein lecha adam hamavir chavis l'chavero mimakom l'makom, nobody will ever do
it because you'd have to pay because if it's a normal type
of an accident that occurs and you make people liable,
so nobody will ever take the job. Of course, why don't you
just let the market adjust that way? Why don't people then offer
more for the job or let the owners explicitly give exemption if
they want to get workers. But maybe it also means that if
the workers are so poor that they'll take the job because they're
desperate for it, but obviously there'll be injustice in the fact that
they'll have to do that and have to pay. Which is interesting,
how much injustice is it if we're really claiming negligence? So it
raises interesting questions. But anyway, חז"ל Chazal thought that it was important
to do this in order that people would be willing to take
the job. They needed to be protected in this way. And this
by the way explains רב אלעזר. Reb Elazar. רב אלעזר Reb Elazar
says I don't understand this, there's negligence, you should be paying, but
that is the הלכה. Halacha. So here's the answer. You know why
it's the הלכה? Halacha? It was a special תקנה takana to protect
the workers. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: היכא נשתבע?
Heicha nishtava? So what type of oath do you take? If you're
basically telling me I think the person was negligent most of the
time, but he's going to be פטור patur anyway to protect the
workers, as long as you... Understand this, there's negligence, you should be
paying, but that is the הלכה. halacha. So here's the answer, you
know why it's the הלכה? halacha? It was a special תקנה takkanah
to protect workers, to protect the workers. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, היכי נשבע? heichi nishba? So what type of oath
do you take? If you're basically telling me I think the person
was negligent most of the time, but he's going to be a
פטור patur anyway to protect the workers as long as he takes
an oath, what's your oath? I wasn't negligent? What type of? You
are negligent. We're assuming you were negligent. But they tripped. What do
you mean? But we're saying that if it really was an accident,
then we wouldn't need this תקנה. takkanah. This תקנה takkanah means that
they were negligent. So what if it was an accident? We still
think you're negligent, so what's your oath? That you, what's the importance
of saying exactly that?
In other words, it broke.
It was an accident rather than what's the alternative, meaning what are
you trying to exclude? What possibility are you trying to exclude? Not
lack of negligence, but that I broke it on purpose. That I
broke it on purpose. Okay, so it's not that I wasn't negligent,
because we're assuming that accidents don't just happen, you were negligent, but
the point is it wasn't intentional. So היכי נשבע? heichi nishba? אמר
רבה, Amar Rava, רבה, Rava, שבועה שלא בכוונה שברתיה. shvua shelo bekavana
shevartia. I did not break it intentionally. Okay, yes, it was an
accident. Fine, maybe you'll tell me I could have been more careful,
but nevertheless, it wasn't intentional.
Okay, ואתא רב יהודה למימר. v'ata Rav Yehuda leimar. Now רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda comes, now we're just going to revisit, like repeat what
we just said yesterday, but now we have a better explanation of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does say it's negligence,
but there's a special תקנה takkanah to get him off. ואתא רב
יהודה למימר: v'ata Rav Yehuda leimar: No, I don't buy this special
תקנה. takkanah. Everybody, people pay at the right level, and the right
level here is a שומר שכר shomer sachar pays and a שומר
חנם shomer chinam does not. שומר חנם ישבע, shomer chinam yishava, שומר
חנם shomer chinam takes an oath. נושא שכר ישלם, nosei sachar yishalem,
somebody who's being, you know, a paid guardian pays. האי כדיניה והאי
כדיניה, hai kedinei v'hai kedinei, each one according to their הלכה, halacha,
there's no middle level of negligence. ואתא רבי אלעזר למימר, v'ata Rabbi
Elazar leimar, אין, in, yes, גמרא כרבי מאיר, Gemara k'Rabbi Meir, but
the tradition is like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ומי תמהני, u'mi tameihani,
I'm astounded, היאך יכולים זה וזה לישבע? heich yecholim zeh v'zeh lishava?
How could they take an oath? בשלמא שומר חנם ישתבע שלא פשע
בה, bishlama shomer chinam yishtava shelo pasha bah, I get a שומר
חנם, shomer chinam, I fundamentally agree with רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, it's
not כנסיות kensios full negligent, it's only partial negligent, so a שומר
חנם shomer chinam should swear and be off. אלא שומר שכר אמאי
משתבע? ela shomer sachar amai mishtava? Why does a שומר שכר shomer
sachar do it? He should be paying. And שומר... אפילו לא פשע
נמי איבעי ליה לשלומי, afilu lo pasha nami ibai lei leshalumei, even
if he wasn't negligent he should pay, and this certainly is not
completely out of your hands, certainly a שומר שכר shomer sachar should
be paying. ואפילו שומר חנם נמי, v'afilu shomer chinam nami, even a
שומר חנם shomer chinam to say that he wasn't negligent. התינח במקום
מדרון, hatinach bemakom midron, that's fine if he had to be going
down an incline, sometimes accidents happen and you really don't aren't negligent.
שלא במקום מדרון, shelo bemakom midron, on a flat level ground, מי
מצי משתבע שלא פשע? mi matzi mishtava shelo pasha? How could you
swear you didn't, we weren't negligent? If you tripped over your own
two feet on level ground, that's negligence. ואפילו במקום מדרון, v'afilu bemakom
midron, even going down an incline, נמי התינח היכא דליכא ראיה, nami
hatinach heicha d'leika reaya,
that's if there's no evidence, then the oath would work. היכא דאיכא
ראיה, heicha d'ika reaya, there is evidence, יביא ראיה ויפטר, yavi reaya
v'yipater, bring a proof. דתניא איסי בן יהודה אומר, d'tanya Isi ben
Yehuda omer, אין רואה, ein roeh, there's nobody who sees it, שבועת
ה' תהיה בין שניהם. shvuat Hashem tihye bein shneihem. הא יש רואה,
ha yesh roeh, somebody does see it, יביא ראיה ויפטר, yavi reaya
v'yipater, you have to bring evidence and then you'll be exempt. Okay,
so that's two ways of reading it, and obviously this way of
reading it introduces that the reason could very well be, yes, you
should be paying in a lot of these cases, but there's a
special תקנה takkanah to protect the workers.
Now we have a couple of real-world cases that illustrate some of
these issues, partly actually this איסי בן יהודה Isi ben Yehuda which
was brought just as an aside, and some of these other issues.
Let's take a look. הגמרא haGemara says like this: ההוא גברא דהוה
קא מעבר חביתא דחמרא בריסתקא דמחוזא. hahu gavra d'hava ka ma'avar chavita
d'chamra beristaka d'Mechuza.
So a person was carrying a, you know, a barrel of wine
in the, in the road of מחוזא, Mechuza, in some type of
a street. ותברה בזיזא דמחוזא, u'tvra beziza d'Mechuza, and he broke it
on some type of a protruding beam that was coming out in
the middle of the road. Okay, so אתא לקמיה דרבה, ata lekamei
d'Rava, and so he came to רבה. Rava. אמר ליה ריסתקא דמחוזא
שכיחי בה אינשי. amar lei ristaka d'Mechuza shechichi bei inshi.
So presumably this was a case where it's not clear. Is this
the same level of negligence as tripping or is not? Was he
a שומר חנם, shomer chinam, a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? But anyway,
it was some case where had, where he if he would
swear maybe רבה's Rava talking about the שבועה shvua that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said. Maybe you really should be paying, but we give
you a שבועה shvua to get you exempt. So it's not exactly
clear what the, how to assess the case in terms of level
of negligence. But the point was, was that he could have taken
a שבועה shvua and been off. That would have been the basic
response. But רבה Rava is not letting him take a שבועה. shvua.
This is now the איסי בן יהודה Isi ben Yehuda position. רבה
Rava is saying you were in the middle of the street. There
must have been people going down the street at that time. Okay,
go ahead and bring witnesses, right? I mean, you know, if I'm...
I know. It's like when you're in a traffic accident, you try
to get the names of all the people that were the witnesses,
right? So and your case is a lot weaker even if you're
not to blame if there were no witnesses. Anyway, that's the point,
right? I agree with you, like how, you know, you're too busy
picking up your broken barrel of wine to be stopping and getting
people's names. So anyway, this is what רבה's Rava response was.
זיל אייתי ראיה ואיפטר. zil aiti reaya v'ipater. Go bring a proof
and be exempt. אמר ליה רב יוסף בריה דרב יוסף, amar lei
Rav Yosef brei d'Rav Yosef, his son said to him, כמאן, כאיסי?
k'man, k'Isi? Who are you going like, like איסי? Isi? That you
required the guy to bring witnesses, he can't just take an oath?
אמר ליה אין כאיסי ומשדרנא כוותיה. amar lei in k'Isi u'mshadrana k'vatieh.
Yes, like איסי, Isi, and we rule that way, which is a
big deal. Right, we've been learning about שומרים shomrim for God knows
how long, right, and here we hear that at least a שומר
חנם, shomer chinam, a שומר shomer in terms of, like שומרים shomrim
can't take a שבועה shvua if there's, if we assume that there're
witnesses available. Now the interesting question is, what does it mean available?
If witnesses saw it, but we don't think it's possible for you
to find out who those witnesses were, right, that's obviously, that's always
the important question, what does it mean if witnesses are available. very
interesting question is, does איסי Issi apply to שבועות shvuot which are
not שבועות השומרים shvuot hashomrim but other types of שבועות? shvuot? Because
one of the questions that the ראשונים rishonim discuss is, what שבועה
shvuah would he have taken? Would he have taken the שבועה shvuah
that he wasn't negligent? Or would he have taken the רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan שבועה? shvuah? Maybe you are negligent but take the רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan שבועה shvuah that you weren't intentional. And then he
says, no no no but you have to if there were witnesses,
you gotta get the witnesses. That's like איסי. Issi. So the relevance
of that is is do we פוסקן pasken like איסי Issi that
you have to that you can't use a שבועה shvuah if there
are witnesses, right, in all only in the שומרים shomrim case, which
is the case איסי Issi was talking about, or in all cases
where we talk about a שבועה? shvuah? Yes.
How are witnesses going to know whether it was an accident or
intentional?
They could say, I mean you could tell, certainly if something looked
intentional, I mean you could say what did you see? I mean
it's a good question, what's your default? Is your default to assume
it's an accident unless there's evidence of being intentional? Is your default
to assume it wasn't negligent unless there's evidence of negligence? Right, that
would make it like easier to say what what the witnesses were
saying. It didn't like you know if you're a good actor you
could make it look like an accident and it was intentional, right?
You never fully know. But I agree, I mean there is a
question about what's the default? What do you need evidence of? Evidence
of negligence or evidence of lack of negligence? Right? That's also a
good question. I don't know.
Also what about the people who intentionally break things?
Right. Okay, right. Right. It is funny to think that this שבועה
shvuah would be to address the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan תקנה. takana.
Because a) it would be very rare that people would intentionally do
it. And presumably the whole nature of that תקנה takana was to
make life, you know, to protect the interest of the worker to
say here just take this שבועה, shvuah, right, to to say that
now you have to get witnesses or whatever, right, but so yes,
I agree with that.
The middle position between negligent and accidental is just poor judgment, right?
Right, well that's presumably the שומר שכר shomer sachar category, correct. That's
correct. And we don't know was he a שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, right, so it's a little unclear what
פסק psak to derive from this, which is why it's discussed in
the ראשונים. rishonim. Okay. Now another story. ההוא גברא דאמר לחבריה, Hahu
gavra d'amar l'chaverey, somebody says to his friend, זיל זבין לי ארבע
מאה דני דחמרא. zil zavin li arba me'ah dany d'chamra. Go buy
for me 400 barrels of wine. Here's $400 or whatever, go buy
400 barrels of wine. אזל זבין ליה, azal zavin lei, he went
and bought it. ולסוף אתא לקמיה, u'lesof ata l'kamei,
and then he came to him, אמר ליה זביני לך ארבע מאה
דני דחמרא, amar lei zvini lach arba me'ah dany d'chamra, I bought
for you 400 barrels of wine, ותקיפו להו, v'takifu lehu, and they
all turned to vinegar. Now, the guy who sent it, gave him
the 400 dollars, is suspicious. Maybe what you really bought was 400
barrels of vinegar for $200 and you pocketed the other 200 for
yourself. Okay? So אזל לקמיה דרבא. azal l'kamei d'Rava. He came to
רבא. Rava. אמר ליה ארבע מאה דני חמרא דתקיפי, קלא אית להו
למילתא. amar lei arba me'ah dany chamra d'takifi, qola it lehu l'milta.
So
if 400 barrels of wine were to turn to vinegar, there would
be people would be talking about it. Oh my god, did you
hear what happened? פלוני Ploni bought, you know, these wine, 400 barrels,
and they all turned to vinegar. So there would be, you know,
there's obviously some people have would know about this issue.
That's like a ראיה rayah in a way.
Well right. וכי אית ליה למילתא קלא. v'chi it lei l'milta qol.
Wait. זיל אייתי ראיה דמעיקרא כי מזבנשת חמרא מעליא הוי ואיפטר. zil
ayty rayah d'me'ikara ki mizavneish chamra ma'alya havay v'ipatir. Go bring proof
that
when you bought it, it was wine, and then you'll be exempt.
Meaning that people would discuss, like, like if there was if people
were saying, you know, so-and-so had this, so-and-so's wine turned to vinegar,
that would be evidence that it turned to vinegar under your possession.
If you can't bring anybody that has heard about this wine that
turned to vinegar, you know, then presumably we're gonna presume that you
bought vinegar. You didn't buy wine that turned to vinegar. If you
had bought wine that turned to vinegar, then everyone would be talking
about it. And now, of course, the question is, but what are
they saying? Are they saying that I saw it? Are they saying,
'Oh yeah, my friend told me about this story.' 'Where'd the friend?'
'I don't know, I heard it in the store.' 'I heard it
from whatever.' So maybe maybe that's true. Maybe it's just the rumor
is enough evidence or is enough to, you know, to to
make us feel, you know, more confident that you're not that, you
know, that it's not the alternative. If the presence of the rumor
produces, it's not direct proof of what happened, but it produces some
evidence towards that. But again, then this becomes very strange because again
this is not a שומרים shomrim case. This is the idea that
if evidence is available we don't trust your שבועה shvuah in something
that has nothing to do with שומרים, shomrim, right? A) It's not
clear here if there were evidence would we need a שבועה? shvuah?
Would it be המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה hamotzi m'chavero alav harayah like
what would be the הלכה halakha if it weren't for this issue
of of evidence? But anyway it seems like a use of איסי
Issi in a case that it's not clearly not a שבועת השומרים
shvuat hashomrim and also that it's not direct evidence, right? It seems
to be
more of a case of supporting, you know, circumstantial evidence as opposed
to direct evidence to the case itself. Let's just read the next
line I'll take the questions. Anyway, so אתא לקמיה, ata l'kamei, that's
what רבא Rava said. אמר רב יוסף בריה דרבא. amar Rav Yosef
brei d'Rava. Rav
Yosef the son of Rava said, כמאן, כאיסי? k'man, k'Issi? Who are
you going like? Like איסי? Issi? So אמר ליה, אין, amar lei
in, כאיסי. Yes, like איסי, Issi, ושרירן כוותיה v'sharian k'vatesei and we
hold like him. Michael, question.
Yeah, I was gonna say, I mean, you know, to me, if
you really wanted to know whether it was wine or vinegar, you
should go ask the seller, right? You know, but then the problem
is, you know, you're maybe you can't tell her to take that
kind of a.
Yeah, that's an interesting question. Why not bring the seller? I don't
know, maybe he's getting a kickback from the whole thing too, you
know. Hey, I'm supposed to buy 400 barrels of wine, I'll get
400. But 400 barrels of vinegar, I'll give you half the difference
or something. But I don't know, you're right, why not get that?
And what does it mean a ראיה? raya? Does ראיה raya mean
two witnesses, one witness, any type of... does it mean that you
have to bring any circumstantial evidence? Let's say it's not about people
testifying, right? So it really opens up like a wide range of
questions here. Yeah, Jonas?
I was wondering if maybe
the... what he's saying is that there's a guy out there selling
wine that turns to vinegar in two days. Like, everyone's going to
be talking about it because other people are also...
oh, to avoid buying from that guy.
Right, like there's going to be like talk about the seller who...
so maybe not like talk that you specifically bought...
ah, but talk that somebody sold wine that turned to vinegar. Right,
that could be too. Right, that wine that was won... was sold
to turn to vinegar and then right. Of course,
if you're smart, you go to the market, you hear the people
are talking about somebody else who sold wine, and then you... so
you have to, you know, seize that sort of opportunity. Yes, Jeremy?
Is the guy assigned to buy the wine a שומר shomer or
a שליח? shaliach?
Yeah, he's a שליח, shaliach, which is again proof that this idea
of Isi is not limited to שומרים, shomrim, right? Okay. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes to...
אשכחיה רב חייא בר יוסף בסיכרא. Ashkacheih Rav Chiyya bar Yosef be-Sichra.
So רב חייא בר יוסף Rav Chiyya bar Yosef established in סיכרא,
Sichra, which is the name of some town.
הני דדרו באגרא ואיתבר. Hani didaru be-agra ve-itbar. Those people that were
carrying on a... an אגרא agra is a type of, apparently from
what I get from the way רש"י Rashi describes it... Okay, it
was a type of a... of a beam of a bar used
for carrying weights, right? The guy... somebody would go here, right, and
it would have like a... it would have so... and he's carry
this on his shoulder, right, and he'd like carry like weights, like
this. Okay? So it'd... it would have like a curve around it
and a beam and he'd carry stuff. Okay. So these... they carry
stuff on it... so that's... that's called, I think, an אגרא, agra,
and it broke. Okay. So he was carrying bundles like this and
he tripped and they broke. משלמי פלגא, Meshalmi palga, pay half. Because
it's like half negligence. Why half negligence? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? נפיש
לחד וזוטר לתרי. Nafish le-chad ve-zutra le-trei. This type of a stuff
normally if you like fully load this up, the weight is too
much for one person or too much for one trip, but it's
not really enough for two trips. Okay? Like this is like me
every single day I go shopping and come back from the garage.
Okay? It's like do I really need a, you know, to go
inside to get the, what do you call it, cart, come back
out? No, no, no, I'll do it all in one trip, right?
And it's like it's not really one trip, but is it really
worth two trips? Okay. So anyway, so in that case,
so... okay.
נפיש לחד וזוטר לתרי. Nafish le-chad ve-zutra le-trei. קרוב לאונס וקרוב לפשיעה.
Karov le-ones ve-karov li-pshia. So you're somewhere between אונס ones and פשיעה.
pshia. And therefore you pay half. Now I gotta tell you, I
don't understand this. Somewhere between אונס ones and פשיעה, pshia, my understanding
that that was the level of a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. So
if you're in the שומר שכר shomer sachar category, you pay full.
If you're in the שומר חנם shomer chinam category, you pay nothing.
You know, the ראש Rosh reframes it a little bit. The ראש
Rosh makes it sound like it's questionable whether you're פושע poshea or
not. Like it's right on the line. Okay? It's not like, you
know, before I sort of said, you know, here's אונס, ones, right,
here's פשיעה, pshia, and here's גנבה ואבדה, gneiva va-aveida, right? So if
you say it's like between them, that's the שומר שכר shomer sachar
category, right? So then if you're שומר שכר shomer sachar you pay,
if you're שומר חנם... shomer chinam... But if you say no, what
it really means there is like you're like right here. You're somewhere
in the... on that line. We don't know where on that line.
Just over or just under. So since we don't know where on
that line to put you, we're going to say pay half. Which
is still interesting. Why don't we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה? ha-motzi
me-chaveiro alav ha-raya? You know, it's still when... you know, this idea,
I mean it's like a סומכוס Sumchos idea. We don't know so
we split it.
This is a case of poor judgment that can only be proven
as poor judgment after the thing breaks.
Oh, that's maybe a possibility too.
Right, it could have really held it...
at the time I really thought... right, I guess it...
right, that's a good point too, right, that maybe it... so that's
the question. How much poor judgment was it, right? We... it's hard
to know.
It's like when you're balancing your coffee cup on your... yeah, exactly
right, right,
exactly right.
I know I can do this. I... I really could have done
it if it wasn't for the guy who opened the door just
when I was turning the corner. Right. Anyway, okay. So the גמרא...
Gemara... okay. Now we're going to have בדילגא. be-dilga. Now if you
carry it on a דילגא, dilga, which is some other type of
a beam that רש"י Rashi says that clearly is meant for like
two people to do and you did it as a one-person job.
In that case, משלם כולא, meshaleim kula, you pay fully. רבה בר
בר חנה... Rabba bar bar Chana... some call it בר חנא... bar
Chana... תברו ליה הני שקולאי. tabru leh hani shakulai. Now this is
a great case to end the פרק. perek. The following line we're
about to reach... we're about to reach is quoted all the time.
Okay, so רבה בר בר חנה, Rabba bar bar Chana, his workers,
שקולאי, shakulai, his porters, broke a חביתא דחמרא, chavita de-chamra, a barrel
of wine. So... and presumably they were negligent. I mean, the question
is how do we פסקן pasken here, but let's say they were
being paid and they... He made them a שומר שכר shomer sachar
category, let's say he פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Anyway,
the presumption was was that it was the level in which they
would be liable. Okay,
שקל גלימייהו, shakal glimae, he took their cloak. אתו אמרו לרב, atu
amru le-Rav, they came and they said to Rav. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so הב להו גלימייהו, hav lehu glimaihu, give them their cloak
back. He was holding onto it until they paid him for his
wine and they complained to Rav, hey he took our coat. So
Rav said give them their coats back. אמר ליה דינא הכי, amar
lei dina hachi, is that really the law? I mean they broke
my wine. They owe it to me. I'm entitled to like you
know hold their property until they pay me. Are you? That's what
I mean. Alright, we're not dealing with that, but let's assume yes,
the פשט p'shat is that they're liable for me. אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said to him, אין, in, yes, that is the law,
למען תלך בדרך טובים, lemaan telech be-derech tovim, so you should do
the right thing, you should go in the paths of of you
know of good righteous people. Which is like that doesn't sound like
דין, din, that sounds like לפנים משורת הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. That
sounds like it's the righteous thing to do, not necessarily what's legally
obligated. But let's keep on going. יהיב להו גלימייהו, yahiv lehu glimaihu,
he gave them their cloaks. אמר ליה, amar lei, so they said
so they said to Rav, עניי אנן, anei anan, we're poor, ותרכינן
כולי יומא, ve-tarchinan kulei yoma, we worked the whole day for our
wages, וכפינן, ve-chafinan, and we're hungry, וליתן מידי, ve-leitan midi, we don't
have anything. Right, presumably he couldn't even just withhold their wages, that
wouldn't have been enough to pay, that's why he had to seize
their cloaks. So now, maybe he just wants to hold back their
wages, get at least partial payment for his wine, and they say
what are we supposed to do? We worked all day, we're going
to go back with no money, we have to put food, we
have to you know food on the table. אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said to whoever this was, רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah
bar bar Chana, he said to him, זיל הב להו אגרייהו, zil
hav lehu agraihu, go pay them their their you know their fee.
You didn't sue them in court for the barrel?
No, don't sue them in court for the barrel. Just pay them
and let it go.
Okay, so אמר ליה דינא הכי, amar lei dina hachi, is that
the law? אמר ליה amar lei, אין, yes, וארחות צדיקים תשמור, ve-orchot
tzaddikim tishmor, you should observe the right not just to טוב tov
but the צדיק, tzaddik, you should do the righteous thing. So even
just withholding their money to pay towards what they weren't paying you
wouldn't have to? Right, because they were poor. Now this is a
גמרא Gemara that is quoted a lot in the discussions of like
לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, right, because it's talking about going
beyond the letter of the law. Now תוספות Tosafot does ask like
that why it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara here doesn't use
the phrase לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, right? And the גמרא
Gemara and תוספות Tosafot actually says לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin
actually has more broader application. Like this is saying if you want
to do the righteous thing, if you want to like be a
צדיק, tzaddik, this is what a צדיק tzaddik would do. And you're
a צדיק, tzaddik, you know, you're רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah bar
bar Chana, you're an אמורא, Amora, whatever, anyway. But but לפנים משורת
הדין lifnim mishurat hadin often is a lower level. It means like
that's more like the spirit of the law. Yes, you could claim
an exemption, you know, like the גמרא Gemara of זקן ואינו לפי
כבודו, zaken ve-eino le-fiv kevodo, should I bow down bend down and
pick up the אבידה, aveidah, you know, like don't claim every exemption
that's coming to you, you know, that's a type of like לפנים
משורת הדין lifnim mishurat hadin type of a thing. It's a more
of a you know yes there's a technicality you can get out
of this, you know, but you shouldn't be playing with technicalities. This
תוספות Tosafot says is a higher level, it's not תוספות Tosafot here,
another תוספות, Tosafot, that if you really they really are liable and
we're asking you to forgo what by דין din is coming to
you, you know, because to do the righteous thing, they're poor people
and so on. Which is funny because again the language of דינא
הכי dina hachi is this the דין, din, right? It's not like
this is what I'm obligated, this is what I should do, is
this the דין? din? You know? So for you, you know, so
it is very good interesting the use of the word דין. din.
The other thing of course to consider here is that the conclusion
of this is not very different than רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Remember
what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said? What did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say? Workers break a barrel and what does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say? Get out of it. Take an oath you should pay, but
take an oath that you didn't do it intentionally and you don't
pay, and then presumably you get paid for your work for that
day. So this issue, and I think this is often lost in
people that discuss this story in the גמרא, Gemara, you know, this
story here is really
reflecting a broader phenomenon of protecting workers' interest, whatever they actually did.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to make a regular תקנה takanah to exactly
have this conclusion, right? So it's not like it's so exceptional you
always should forgo. You broke you rammed into my car but you're
a poor person so therefore I should just let it go. Right?
There's broader you know systemic issues here that even led to a
תקנה takanah for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So that's also like important
to to consider, yes.
Interesting though but like you know with this change let's say רבה
בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana also is poor. This just
is like you know...
yeah... it might have it maybe it would have changed. It might
it very well might have changed, yeah.
Has everyone here seen the movie Do the Right Thing?
I don't think so.
Okay I won't give a spoiler.
Then it relates to it. Alright fine. הדרן עלך השוכר את האומנין.
Hadran alach ha-socher et ha-umnin.
This is like the flip side of saying that if they didn't
have that the Rabbis didn't institute that law about taking the oath
the workers wouldn't be liable, so here you see it on the
other side. The person who is hiring, right, he might be concerned
about what he's going to...
Right, well that's an excellent point too. Like whenever you say we're
protecting this side of it, like are you sort of you know
thinking about like that's the whole field of like economics and law.
Are you thinking about then how is you know how's the whole
you know system going to adjust to deal with that and who
are you hurting as a result of trying to protect this side?
Right.
I mean they'd be wary of hiring.
Right exactly. I get it. That's a point. Right to protect this
side what does that do to the other side? Right. Okay. Moving
on to the next פרק *Perek*, השוכר את הפועלים *Hassocher Et HaPoalim*,
hiring workers. Now השוכר *Hassocher* is the word, only a craftsman, but
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* has the word אומן *Uman*. I mentioned this when
we started השוכר *Hassocher*, so אומן *Uman* covers both people that are
paid for the job, which are קבלן *Kablan*, right, a contractor, and
like daily laborers. פועלים *Poalim* for תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* is much more
generally narrow and refers to daily laborers. Okay, so you hire these
workers, ואמר להם להשכים ולהעריב *Ve'amar Lahem Lehashkim Uleha'ariv*, and you told
them I expect you to come to work, you know, bright and
early and you're going to stay late. Okay? Sounds like most modern
employers today. מקום שנהגו שלא להשכים ושלא להעריב אינו רשאי לכופן *Makom
Shenahagu Shelo Lehashkim Veshelo Leha'ariv Eino Rashai Lekofan*. But if the practice
is not to get up early and stay late, he can't force
them. Even regular business hours. Right, regular business hours. Now, the question
is, what do you mean he can't force them? They specifically
stipulated, right? Who cares what the מנהג minhag. *Minhag* is? The מנהג
minhag, *Minhag* is you work nine to five, I go and I
hire you and I say, I'm hiring you but I want you
to be working from eight to six. So, you agreed to it,
we all agreed, then you say, ha ha, what, I'm not going
to do it because the מנהג *Minhag* is nine to five? So
look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*. השוכר את הפועלים ואמר להם להשכים ולהעריב
*Hassocher Et HaPoalim Ve'amar Lahem Lehashkim Uleha'ariv*. פירש ר״י *Peirush Ri*, בששכרן
סתמא *Besheshacharan Stama*, when we initially hired you, we didn't say any
stipulation. ואמר להם אחר ששכרן *Ve'amar Lahem Achar Sheshacharan*, and after I
hired you, I went and I said, by the way, I want
you to be coming early and staying late. Okay? כבר ששכרן *Kevar
Sheshacharan*, ואמר להם אחר ששכרן כבר להשכים ולהעריב *Ve'amar Lahem Achar Sheshacharan
Kevar Lehashkim Uleha'ariv*. After I already
hired you, then I said. Then I could say, oh, what I
say doesn't mean anything because I already hired you and that was
the practice, etc. אבל אם התנה מעיקרא *Aval Im Hitna Mei'ikara*, if
it was an initial stipulation, הכל לפי תנאו *Hakol Lefi Tena'o*, of
course you can make whatever stipulations you want. Okay, now maybe not,
you know, maybe there's laws or there's something known as employment laws,
right? I can't stipulate, we can't say, well if you agree to
accept, you know, fifty cents an hour, you agreed to it. But
it's not clear because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to stay
on this פשיטא Pshita, *Pshita*. So, again theoretically you could say that
there are like employment laws to protect the workers, but then it
wouldn't be based on מנהג *Minhag*, then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* would
not say פשיטא *Pshita*. So the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
sort of thinks that this first line, that this thing is based
on מנהג *Minhag* is פשיטא *Pshita*, it seems that תוספות׳ס *Tosfos's* reading
is a reasonable one. That this was not the initial stipulation, but
you could obviously stipulate, you know, contrary to this.
Yeah, but so what I don't understanding because yeah exactly, במקום שנהגו
*Bimakom Shenahagu*, let's say there is no מנהג *Minhag*, right?
Or let's say there's a מנהג *Minhag* of... so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to deal with that. Okay, we'll deal with that.
מקום שנהגו לזון יזון *Makom Shenahagu Lazun Yazun*. Now we're going to
just get to the broader sense of like, you know, without any
explicit stipulation you go by the normal practice. And of course what
Michael says is, let's say there's a diversity of practice. But let's
anyway take a look here. מקום שנהגו לזון יזון *Makom Shenahagu Lazun
Yazun*. If the normal practice is to feed your workers, you have
to feed them. לספק במתיקה יספק *Lesapek Bemetika Yaspek*. And if the
feeding not only is giving them some bread but giving them some
like nice sweet stuff with it, or רש״י *Rashi* says something to
dip their bread into, you have to. הכל כמנהג המדינה *Hakol Keminnhag
Hamedina*. So not only the fact that you feed them, but what's
considered to be acceptable, you know, food to be given them. מעשה
ברבי יוחנן בן מתיא *Ma'aseh BeRabbi Yochanan Ben Masya* we saw this
once before in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, ששכר פועלים *Sheshachar Poalim*, השוכר
רבי יוחנן בן מתיא *Hassocher Rabbi Yochanan Ben Masya*... no, מעשה ברבי
יוחנן בן מתיא שאמר לבנו *Ma'aseh BeRabbi Yochanan Ben Masya She'amar Livno*,
he said to his son, צא שכור לנו פועלים *Tze Sechor Lanu
Poalim*, go hire for us some workers for today. והלך ופסק להם
מזונות *Vehalach Ufasak Lahem Mezonot*, he went and he agreed to give
them food. וכשבא אצל אביו *Ucheshe'ba Etzel Aviv* he came to his
father, אמר לו *Amar Lo*, בני *Bni*, אפילו אם אתה עושה להם
כסעודת שלמה בשעתו *Afilu Im Atah Oseh Lahem Kise'udat Shlomo Bish'ato*, even
if you were to feed them like a feast like שלמה *Shlomo*
had when he was at the height of his kingdom, לא יצאת
ידי חובתך עמהם *Lo Yatzata Yedei Chovatcha Imahem*, you would not fulfill
your obligation with them, שהן בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב *Shehen Bnei Avraham
Yitzchak VeYaakov* and therefore they're deserving of like great, you know, to
treat them as kings and princes. אלא עד שלא יתחילו במלאכה *Ela
Ad Shelo Yatchilu Bimlacha* before they start the work, because if they
start without that agreement then we're fully liable, but beforehand it was
not yet binding. It only becomes binding once the work starts. You
might remember before when the whole question was somebody backed out, do
they have to pay for the day, did they show up for
the work, not show up for the work. So the contract only
becomes binding once the work starts. So before the work starts, so
צא ואמור להם *Tze Ve'emor Lahem* go say to them, על מנת
שאין לכם עלי אלא פת וקטנית בלבד *Al Menat She'ein Lachem Alai
Ela Pat Vekitnit Bilvad*. No, no, I want to clarify, the only
thing I'm liable to provide is like, you know, some lentils and
some bread.
So even if
there was a מנהג *Minhag*... well, right, so well we don't know.
So the question here is, why when he said that I'll feed
you, would that have meant I'll feed you as, you know, fully
what you deserve? Why don't we say that that agreement, I'll feed
you, is defined by the מנהג המדינה minhag hamedina. *Minhag Hamedina*? We
just said that it goes by the מנהג המדינה *Minhag Hamedina*. So
the מנהג המדינה *Minhag Hamedina* is if you say nothing, but if
you're explicit and you say you'll feed then all of a sudden
it means like a maximum amount? It's like not clear how this
story works with the previous thing. Maybe the problem was he said,
I will feed you whatever you want or whatever's appropriate. And then
that's what his father was saying, well appropriate means like whatever. But
it's not clear again why, what, why do you have to reclarify?
Why don't we say הכל כמנהג המדינה *Hakol Keminnhag Hamedina*? So all
this we'll discuss. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel
Omer*, לא היה צריך לומר *Lo Hayah Tzarich Lomar*, הכל כמנהג המדינה
*Hakol Keminnhag Hamedina*. So that's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel* exactly says back. What, that was all being very nice,
you were being a צדיק *Tzaddik*, but הכל כמנהג המדינה *Hakol Keminnhag
Hamedina*. So what did they hold?
The גמרא Gemara first starts with this idea of when you have
to show up to work. פשיטא, obviously you even if you said
to come early and stay late you you just go by the
מנהג. So again the fact that it says obvious reinforces the idea
that you cannot have been an explicit stipulation when you made it
and it would not at all be obvious. Okay but presumably we'll
go with תוספות'ס Tosafot's read: initially you said nothing, afterwards you said
I expect you to come early and stay late, and it says
they don't have to do that because they because, so the גמרא
Gemara says obviously that's the מנהג המדינה. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, לא צריכא דטפי להו אגריהו. Lo tzricha detafi lehu agrayhu. He
says, he goes and he says you know what I'm actually going
to give you 12 dollars an hour, an hour, but I expect
you to pay you know to stay to come early and stay
late. So מהו דתימא אמרו לו האי דטפית לן אגרא אדעתא דמקדמינן
ומחשכינן בהדך. Ma d'teima amru lei hai detafit lan agra adaita demikadmeinan
umachshicheinan bahadach. So he could say the reason I was paying you
more, not 10 dollars an hour but 12 dollars an hour, was
because I expect you to come early and stay late. קא משמע
לן דאמרו ליה, Ka mashma lan d'amru lei, they could say back
to him,
האי דטפת לן אדעתא דעבדינן לך עבידתא שפירתא. Hai detafit lan adaita
de'avdinan lach avidta shapirta. You wanted us to do an extra good
job. Now again if he explicitly says I'm going to give you
an extra 2 dollars an hour on the understanding that you're going
to come early and stay late, that's different. But if he just
says you know he says I'm giving you 12 dollars an hour,
I mean the same question, how do you interpret like where's the
ambiguity. Let's say he says and not because. I give you know
we agreed 10 dollars an hour, then I come later and I
say you know what it'll be 12 dollars an hour and I
expect you to come early and stay late, right? So how do
you read the and there? Anyway, so it's always an interesting question
about is there enough ambiguity for that claim. אמר ריש
לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish,
said ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, פועל בכניסתו משלו ביציאתו משל בעל הבית.
Poel bichnisato mishelo biytziato mishel ba'al habayis. A פועל poel when he
comes in he it's on his own time, meaning let's see what
that's going to mean is you leave after it gets dark, after
צאת, Tzeis, okay, and you know and the time and therefore your
trip home is on your own time, you're no longer working for
the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, you're going home. ביציאתו משל בעל הבית,
Biytziato mishel ba'al habayis, when he leaves, right, he leaves it's on
the בעל הבית'ס ba'al habayis's time, which means as the גמרא Gemara
the way the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to interpret this means the basic
working hours are presumed to be from sunrise until צאת. Tzeis. Okay
now normally you might say the day begins at you know at
עלות Alos like you know an hour before sunrise, okay but yes
but maybe that's true but when you're getting to your job you
know you are let's well you know actually I take that back.
I'm I'm misexplained this, let me say this one more time. Okay,
sorry. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to interpret this means that when
you come home you're on your own time, let me just find,
forget this specific times. Let me just sort of say what the
statement means. When you come home you're on your own time. When
you're going to work you're on your employer's time, which that would
be nice, right? I only have to leave my house at 9
o'clock.
You know you're on the employer's clock when you when you leave
your house and you're on your own time when you come home.
The way the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to interpret that means that you
leave your house at נץ, Netz, at sunrise, and you come home
at צאת. Tzeis. It's going to interpret it to mean that the
it assumes that the working day is from sunrise until צאת. Tzeis.
So what does that mean sunrise until צאת? Tzeis? You could say
that means I have to get to my job and be there
at sunrise, then I have to get home by צאת, Tzeis, right?
Which is actually תוספות Tosafot actually discusses that's actually a reasonable position
because that means you're traveling before sunrise but it's still already a
little bit light, which is an acceptable time for travel, and you
get home by צאת Tzeis which makes sense because you don't want
to be traveling once it gets fully dark, you want to be
home by the time it's fully dark. So actually that makes sense
and there's one of the בעלי התוספות Ba'alei HaTosafot who tries to
read the גמרא Gemara exactly that way because that is the most
logical. But nevertheless תוספות Tosafot and רש"י Rashi say the פשט pshat
of the גמרא Gemara is the opposite of that. The פשט pshat
of the גמרא Gemara is that you leave your home at sunrise,
so means you actually can get to work maybe an hour or
half hour after sunrise, which seems like that's a lot of wasted
daytime that's gone away, and you leave work at צאת Tzeis which
is and then you travel after it's pretty dark. It's very strange
and תוספות acknowledges it but it's what the גמרא sounds like although
he tries to read the גמרא in the flip. So again the
idea is is that the workday is from sunrise until צאת הכוכבים
Tzeis hakochavim and it's saying for the the when you're going to
work you're on your employer's time so you leave your house at
נץ Netz and when you're going home you're on your own time
so you have to stay at work until צאת. Tzeis. Let's read
this.
כניסתו משלו Knisato mishelo is משלו mishelo means at your own time.
מכניסתו Miknisato means when you get into work it's your time?
No so that's the flip. ביציאתו Biytziato means come into work. But
normally the word כניסתו knisato and certainly that's the פסוק pasuk when
it comes when you're נכנס לעיר nichnas la'ir and ביציאתו biytziato is
when you're יוצא מן הבית yotzei min habayis and you're יוצא yotzei
to work. Okay, so oh maybe that's what was confusing you. Alright
let's read the פסוק, pasuk, it's based on the next פסוק. pasuk.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, it says, תזרח השמש יאספון, Tizrach hashemesh ye'asefun,
when the sun rises they will gather this is talking about the
nocturnal animals... Okay, ואל מעונתם ירבצון ve'el me'onatam yirbatzun and to their
dwelling places they will lie down, these are the nocturnal animals.
יצא אדם לפעלו yetze adam lefo'olo לפעלו lefo'olo a person goes out
to work, so that's יציאתו, yetziato, right? So it's sunrise,
תזרח השמש, tizrach hashemesh, and you are being יוצא, yotze, you are
going out to work, ולעבודתו עדי ערב vela'avodaso adey arev and you
work until night. Okay, so again, you're leaving to go to work
at sunrise, תזרח השמש, tizrach hashemesh, and you're working עדי ערב adey
arev until night. So that's the reading that you leave your home
at sunrise, work from some sunrise till צאת, tzeis, you leave at
sunrise, and you come back after צאת, tzeis, so your so the
workday start is sunrise צאת, tzeis, but the but the going to
work is on your employer's time, and the going home is after
צאת tzeis on your own time. But again, תוספות tries to reread
this in a flip way which makes a lot more sense. Travel
from from עלות, alos, get to work maybe at night, but travel
while it's while it's daylight, you know, while even earlier on so
you have a full day left, but while the day begins to
break, and go home and leave so that you can get home
by צאת. tzeis. But so תוספות tries to read it that way,
but in the end he prefers this reading. Yeah.
And then what should when you דאוון? daven?
Yeah, so that we could do גמרא ברכות. Gemara Berachos. Moving on.
Okay, so okay, let's get let's get a little bit further. גירסא
girsa is like this: Okay, ולחי היכי דנהיגי, velechi heichi dehinhigi, so
the גמרא says let's just see what the practice is. בעיר חדשה
be'ir chadasha it's a new city, okay, so we don't have any
established practice, so we go by the פסוקים. pesukim. ובנהיגי מהיכא קאתו,
uvenehigi meheicha ka'asu,
let's see where the people came from the new city, right? They
didn't just get created יש מאין, yesh me'ayin, they came from somewhere.
Okay, so the גמרא says במכונסיי, bemichunsai, when they're gathered from a
lot of different places, it's a cosmopolitan city, people are coming from
all over. אי בעית אימא I ba'is eima or דאמר להו de'amar
lehu דאגריתו לי כפועלי דאורייתא, de'agrisu li kepo'alei de'Oraisa, or you said
explicitly that no, we're going to go according to the parameters that
are in the תורה, Torah, and here are the parameters in the
תורה. Torah. But it is interesting because the גמרא also acknowledges there
are places that don't have a מנהג, that have a diversity of
מנהגים, minhagim, and then you have to look somewhere else for what
the implicit standards are. Okay, דרש רבא darash Rava ואמרי לה ve'amri
lah ואמרי לה תני רב יוסף, ve'amri lah tani Rav Yosef, מאי
דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse, תשת חושך ויהי לילה,
tashet choshech vihi layla, you know, God makes darkness fall and there's
night, בו תרמוש כל חיתו יער, bo sirmos kol chaiso ya'ar, there
will like
crawl around, wander around all of the, you know, animals of the
forest, the nocturnal animals. תשת חושך ויהי לילה, tashet choshech vihi layla,
so we're going to interpret this as, you know, as a metaphor.
When darkness falls and there's night, זהו עולם הזה zehu olam hazeh
שדומה ללילה, shedomeh lelayla, this this is this world, which is like
nighttime compared to the world to come. בו תרמוש כל חיתו יער,
bo sirmos kol chaiso ya'ar, then all the animals creep, you know,
sort of wander around. So who are the animals? החיה, hachaya, right,
like wild
animals. אלו רשעים elu resha'im שבו shebo in this world, שדומים לחיה
shedomim lechaya שבער, shebeya'ar, they're like these wild animals in the forest.
So they're the ones, meaning in this world, which is like night,
that's when the רשעים resha'im have like the same way, you know,
at nighttime it's the nocturnal animals, the wild animals that have dominion
in the nighttime, in this world, the רשעים resha'im have dominion. Okay,
because this world is night.
תזרח השמש יאספון, tizrach hashemesh ye'asafun, ah, but when the sun rises,
they'll they'll gather in, right, בעולם הבא be'olam haba there won't be
any of those wild animals. ואל מעונתם
ירבצון, ve'el me'onatam yirbatzun, and then to their dwelling places they will
lie down. So תזרח השמש tizrach hashemesh לצדיקים, latzaddikim, when the sun
rises for the righteous in the world to come, יאספון רשעים לגיהנום,
ye'asafun resha'im legehinnom, then they will be gathered in and they'll go
to גיהנום. Gehinnom. ואל מעונתם ירבצון, ve'el me'onatam yirbatzun, and this is
now read this referring to the צדיקים, tzaddikim, the the on their
own time. The צדיקים tzaddikim will lie down in their dwelling places,
אין לך כל צדיק וצדיק ein lecha kol tzaddik vetzaddik שאין לו
מדור לפי כבודו. she'ein lo mador lefi kevodo. Everyone has their own
lair, their own dwelling place, every righteous person has a dwelling place
in the עולם הבא olam haba fit for the level that they've
achieved. יצא אדם לפעלו, yetze adam lefo'olo, a person goes out to
work. יצאו צדיקים לקבל שכרם, yetz'u tzaddikim lekabel secharam, they will go
out to receive their reward for all the work they did in
this world to keep the מצוות. mitzvos. ולעבודתו
עדי ערב, vela'avodaso adey arev, and to their work until nightfall, במי
שהשלים עבודתו עדי ערב, be'mi she'hishlim avodaso adey arev, meaning until the
work that they did until righteous until they died. The one that
will God will reward them not in this world, but after they
die in the world to come. You know, again, it's always so
fascinating, right, because all this is so against the biblical theology, you
know, you do the מצוות mitzvos and get rewarded in this world.
And חז"ל Chazal completely obviously recognize that that's not what happens, right,
so they like read in the פסוקים pesukim like a very explicit
like it's no longer a problem of צדיק ורע לו. tzaddik vera
lo. This is the way it is. This world רשעים resha'im have
שליטה, shlita,
you'll get your reward in the world to come. Okay, רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar barbi Shimon אשכח לההוא פרהגונא. ashkach le'hahu parhagona.
So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar barbi Shimon found a, what
is actually say this פרהגונא parhagona is,
oh right, a oh yeah, this is a great story.
He found an
official, who was like who was appointed by the king, okay, דקא
תפיס גנבי. deka tafis ganavei. He was a policeman. His job was
to seize robbers. אמר ליה היכי יכלת להו,
amar
leh
heichi yachalt lehu, he said, how are you able to, you know,
seize them and to identify them and
to
you know outscheme them? all of the wild animals of the forest
will wander around. So איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri מהאי קרא קאמר ליה,
mehai kra k'amar lei, some say he quoted another פסוק passuk to
him. יארב במסתר כאריה בסכה, Ye'erov b'mistar k'aryeh b'sukkah, they were like
lying in wait like a lion in his like den, okay? So
anyway, how do you, first of all, how are you able to
trap them? And anyway, how do you know you got the right
people? Maybe that's the same question twice. And דלמא שקלת צדיקי ושבקת
רשיעי, v'dilma shakalta tzadiki v'shabakta rishiei, maybe you're seizing innocent people and
letting the guilty go off free. So אמר ליה ומאי אעביד, amar
lei u'mai avid, so what am I supposed to do? הרמנא דמלכא
הוא, Harmana d'malka hu, it's the king's orders. I gotta do it,
the king ordered me. אמר תא אגמרך היכי תעביד, Amar ta agmrecha
heichi taavid, let me teach you how you can identify who the
thieves are, who the גנבים ganavim are. Okay. עול בארבע שעי לחנותא,
Ul b'arba sha'ei l'chanuta, go in at 4 o'clock, at 10:00 AM,
which is when like everybody gets their break for like, I don't
know, a late breakfast. This is the standard worker's break when they
go and they go to the store, coffee break. Well, it's not
a coffee break. They have their meal then, okay? So everybody takes
their break and goes and gets their meal at the diner. So
go to the diner at that time. כי חזית איניש דקשתי חמרא
וקנקי כסא בידיה וקמנמנם, Ki chazis inish d'kashti chamra v'kanki kasa b'yadei
v'kamnamnem, if you see somebody drinking wine and holding a cup in
his hand and dozing off. Okay. So the question is, why are
you dozing off? It's only 10:00 AM. שיילי ליה, Shayli lei, you
know, ask about that person. אי צורבא מרבנן הוא ונומם, Ei tzurva
m'rabanan hu v'numam, if he's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and he's
dozing off and drinking a drink a little early, everything he's drinking
a little early, anyway, אקדומא קדים לגרסיה, akdumei kadim l'garsei, ah, that's
because he gets up really early, like he, you know, they get
up early in the morning in order to learn, like everybody here
with the דף יומי. daf yomi. So that's why by 10 o'clock
he needs a little nap. He'll fall asleep. אי פועל הוא, Ei
poel hu, if he's a worker, קדומא קא עביד עבידתיה, kadumei ka
avid avidteih, he gets up early for his work, which doesn't fit
with the thing there about נץ החמה, Netz HaChamah, right? If you're
getting up early, that's before sunrise. Anyway, but okay, but that's maybe,
but normally you would get up earlier than that. So if it's
a normal day laborer, he got up early. ואי עבידתיה בליליא, V'ei
avidteih b'leilya, if he's a night worker, so he should be sleeping
now. אי רדודי רדיד, Ei ridudei radid, then maybe the reason is
because he was, Rashi says this is somebody that, I don't know,
that deals with like making what do you call it, like metal
strings or something like that. Anyway, some type of a work that
he could be doing at night that could have like brought, you
know, he could have been up all night doing it. And that
would explain why he's sleepy. ואי לא, V'ei lo, but if it's
none of those other explanations, then why is he sleeping? Because what
was he doing at night? He was stealing. גנבא הוא ותפסיה, Ganava
hu v'safsei, then he's a גנב ganav and you should seize him.
Okay. So this is what he said. So here he figured out,
he like knew the strategy or whatever to find it. אשתמע מילתא
בי מלכא, Ishtama milta bei malka, so this was heard in the,
you know, over in the palace. אמרו Amru and they said, this
is such a great line, this is used elsewhere, קרינא דאיגרתא איהו
להוי פרונקא, karyna d'igarta ihu leihavei parvanka, the one who reads the
letter, the proclamation,
he should be the one to execute it. Okay. So it meaning,
what a great idea! You should be the one to carry it
out. You know what you're doing. Guess who now is our new
policeman? You! Okay. So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
became the king's policeman. Okay. אוקמוה לרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון וקא תפיס
גנבי. Okmueh l'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon v'ka tfis ganvei.
Okay.
So then they took רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon.
That he now is the policeman and he was now seizing גנבים.
ganavim. Okay. ואזל שלח ליה רבי יהושע בן קרחה. V'azal shalach lei
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. Now Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha heard that this
חשוב chashuv Rabbi here is, you know, is seizing גנבים. ganavim. And
he said, חומץ בן יין, Chometz ben yayin,
vinegar son of wine, reminds us of our vinegar and wine story
from the first עמוד. amud. Okay. עד מתי אתה מוסר עמו של
אלוהינו להריגה? Ad masai ata moser amo shel eloheinu l'hariga? How long
are you going to give over? Because he was seizing Jewish גנבים.
ganavim. Everybody here is Jewish in the story except for the king.
How often are you going to be, and presumably a גנב ganav
didn't just get thrown into prison, a גנב ganav got killed. So
how long are you going to be, you know, what are you
doing? You're working with the government to send Jews to, you know,
to prison, to get them killed? So this is a very relevant
גמרא because it, I don't know, it comes out elsewhere. Anyway, there's
because it's very relevant nowadays. Like people say, "Can I be a,
can I be a prosecutor? Can I be a policeman? Can I
be this? Can I be that?" right? And are you a מוסר?
moser? And well, right, are you a מוסר? moser? And how do
you know you get the right person? And you know, and how
do you know, let's say, you know, you send somebody to, to
prison and you know, often horrific things can happen in prison and
so on and so. So he says, "How could you be doing
this?" שלח ליה, Shalach lei, he sent back to him, קוצים אני
מכלה מן הכרם. kotzim ani mechaleh min hakerem. I'm getting rid of
the thorns from the vineyard. Yes, actually this is God's work to
actually do this, which is interesting, right? Because it does seem a
little disproportionate to the Torah law, you know, about what's happening. שלח
ליה, Shalach lei, he sent to him, יבא בעל הכרם ויכלה את
קוציו. yavo baal hakerem v'yichaleh es kotzav. Let the owner of the
vineyard come and get rid of the thorns. That's not your responsibility.
That's God's responsibility. Okay. So we will, we will pause here. It's
such a great story and I don't want to rush through the
rest. I will leave it where I will leave you with a
cliffhanger in the middle of what's going to happen with this story
here
of the Jews. It's such a great story and I don't want
to rush through the rest. I will leave where I will leave
you with a cliffhanger in the middle of what's going to happen
with this story here of the Jewish policeman and the Jewish גנב.
ganav.